George Henry Dern Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
George Henry Dern Papers 1933-1936
MSS18325
Dern, George Henry, 1872-1936
2,100 items
6 containers
2.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Cabinet officer and governor of Utah. Correspondence, speeches, radio addresses, statements, memoranda, photographs, and other material dealing chiefly with Dern’s daily activities as secretary of war.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Dern, George Henry, 1872-1936.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.
Organizations
Governors' Conference.; United States. War Department.
Subjects
Governors--United States.
Places
Mississippi River--Description and travel.; Panama--Description and travel.; Philippines--Description and travel.; Saint Lawrence Seaway--Description and travel.
Occupations
Cabinet officers.; Governors--Utah.
Provenance
The papers of George Henry Dern, cabinet officer and governor of Utah, were given to the Library of Congress in 1948 by his wife, Charlotte Brown Dern.
Other Repositories
Collections of Dern’s Papers can also be found in the Utah State Archives, the National Archives and Records Administration, the Franklin D. Roosevelt Library, and the Utah Historical Society.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of George Henry Dern are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of George Henry Dern (1872-1936) span the period 1933-1936 and include correspondence, speeches, radio addresses, statements, memoranda, photographs, and other material dealing with Dern’s daily activities as secretary of war under Franklin D. Roosevelt.
The files relate chiefly to Dern’s inspection trips, particularly those to the Mississippi River and the St. Lawrence Seaway; formal and ceremonial occasions, such as a governor’s conference in California in 1933; and trips to Panama and the Philippines.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material and chronologically thereunder.
Container List
- Chronological file (Box 1)
  - 1933 (Box 1)
    - Mar. 17-July 22, (17 folders) (Box 1)
    - July 24, (1 folder); (3 folders) (Box 1, Box 2)
    - Aug. 7-Sept. 16, (7 folders) (Box 2)
    - Oct. 4-Nov. 11, (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1934 (Box 3)
    - Feb. 22-Sept. 11, (13 folders) (Box 3)
    - Oct. 4-Nov. 26, (6 folders) (Box 4)
  - 1935 (Box 4)
    - Jan. 30-Mar. 19, (5 folders) (Box 4)
    - Mar. 26-Dec. 12, (10 folders) (Box 5)
  - 1936 (Box 5)
    - Jan. 12-Feb. 28, (6 folders) (Box 5)
    - Apr. 2-19, (3 folders) (Box 6)
- Correspondence, 1933-1936, (10 folders) (Box 6)
- Messages, 1933-1936, (2 folders) (Box 6)